<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Satwik's Blog</title>
    <description>My ideas and thoughts</description>
    <link>/my_page/</link>
    <atom:link href="/my_page/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 15:22:51 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 15:22:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Random Musings</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A little while ago, while studying some scientific theory, owing to perhaps some deep-rooted stochastic neural process that dictates how trains of thoughts travel across the mental landscape, I embarked on a journey that culminated in what I so interestingly (or pointlessly, depending on your position on the glass-full-empty scale) report in the ensuing article. I promise, no self praises here on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often overlook how deeply entrenched is Statistics in Science and the implications of such an intimate intertwining. Discounting deep philosophical arguments, Science ultimately craves an understanding of the esoteric natural processes, constantly needing the satisfaction of theorizing something and then ‘confirming’ it by experiment to sustain its overly curious meta-body. Almost all of our understanding of the world rests on the ‘fact’ that rare events rarely happen, and hence, we are more likely living in a world which functions in such a way that what we observe is common, rather than the one in which it is rare. This idea is central to interpreting the results of every single inquiry ever set forth by Science. But if we entirely rest our body of knowledge on the foundations of probabilistic conclusions, then this entire edifice becomes vulnerable to what every Random Variable is vulnerable to - Randomness (Duh?). 
Imagine this. Someone comes up with a drug which is supposed to cure X. We perform 10 RCTs with 10000 people each, and every one of the 50000 in the drug group is cured of X and everyone in the control group dies (or any equivalent euphemism) of X. A probabilistic conclusion goes thus: Since what we observed would be very rare if the drug were not effective, we should conclude that it is effective; since given that, the observation becomes much more likely, which is in line with our ‘rare events happen rarely’. But what if this event was truly rare? There is a finite possibility that the drug actually works in a way that kills 9 out of 10 people it is given to, and the disease X only kills 8 out of 10 without treatment, so in ‘reality’ (if that exists  ), the drug is indeed poisonous. But, if this selection of people (9 of the 10) is truly random, then there is a finite possibility that our RCTs happen given this ‘truth’ no matter how well the two groups were randomized and balanced in potential confounders. If that has actually happened, we might just legalize the drug and it starts killing everyone from next day on, as it was always more likely to do! (Something like if a tails is less probable than a heads for a particular coin, TTT….TTTT is still possible, and the next event in case of an independent draw would mostly be an H.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Alas! Of course, there are several caveats to this (also there is tons of debate about p-value based testing not being evidence, so not really a novel What-If). The assumption that the selection of the 9 of 10 people being actually random is usually not the case; there are confounders and other biases at play. All this complexity is always present in the ‘real world’ such that the outcomes are hardly ever truly random. So then the question comes, is there any truly random process determining the natural-process outcomes? And to the rescue of my thought train, there are tons of them, from protein binding to gene expression. The entire molecular machinery is random, guided by statistical thermodynamic along entropy gradients! A drug might actually bind to target A million times better than B, but if this process is truly random, it might actually someday end up binding to B in all cases in an RCT we conduct! But let us go even deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limitations of perfectly describing processes of nature in terms of deterministic equations had long been theorized, but the intrinsic need of humans to grab on to something concrete and ‘meaningful’ like determinism led to the theorizers being disagreed with. Their vindication came with the oncoming of Quantum Mechanics which showed that the very fabric of nature might, after all, be indeterministic, and that God indeed is a Casino dealer, duping us into believing we can gamble on basis of some pattern we seemingly see to this madness. What QM depends upon is the observation that the very behaviour of particles is indeterministic, stochastic, random (choose your poison). But we still have some pattern to this madness we encode in terms of probabilities of energies, positions and several arcane attributes these particles can have, and these probabilities seem to constraint the randomness into understandable chunks. Building from these, let us assume we reach the assumptions we make at the macro level, i.e. someone, starting from these probabilities, do actually end up proving that the probability of there being such a huge difference in an RCT of the drug is very low if the drug does absolutely nothing in the body (or is harmful). He might make the outcomes almost deterministic since most of the randomness we observe at such a level is the result of unknown underlying confounders/determinants. By characterizing all of these, he might end up directly linking the Quantum probabilities to those in the RCT; but if the very fabric is random, there still exists some probability that any tapestry made of that fabric bears the burden of the possibility of an extremely rare event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us move one step further. What if the very act of trying to find a meaningful description of the universe is flawed in itself? What if the ‘rules’ of physics, and QM, which we assume the universe follows, actually do not exist the way we think they do? What if the universe decides every picosecond to arbitrarily act in some way, and it just so happened that those arbitrations lined up perfectly for all this while for us to draw some conclusions, believing that there is some logic to these rules, but actually they are just arbitrary fragments of a stochastic oneness? What if tomorrow everything stops behaving the way we would expect it to, and random arbitrary happenings commence? Why, the very laws of conservation of energy and momentum and the like, which are the basic most of the ‘assumptions’ underlying a lot of scientific theory, depend on the isotropicity of space and time (i.e. loosely speaking, the fact that laws of physics do not change over time or space), and this is purely an experimental observation, ever susceptible to a future experiment disproving it! We might be in an isotropic patch of an anisotropic universe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last occupant of Pandora’s box never seemed so dear!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purpose of an analogy, imagine a huge building found upon a large pillar (sort of like the Pantheon but with only one pillar and a huge building instead of the roof, which makes it as less like Pantheon as one can be. But still, go on.). People every day brought tons of concrete and dumped on the tower to constantly raise it further, hoping to be able to one day see (or as they called it, understand) completely the world from atop it, as taller the building, the more they thought they could see. But on closer inspection, someone realizes that the base column might not exist, (perhaps might only be an optical illusion), which implies that the entire structure above it might also not exist and all the concrete they had been dumping was just pure nothingness; the building might be duping the onlookers into believing they were indeed seeing something when all the while what they were seeing were random visions of different parts of the world brought in by the drifting winds, infinitely contorted to perfectly flummox any attempt at piecing together of the world that the people seemed to endeavor on. The best part, they were not sure whether the pillar existed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>/my_page/articles/21/Random-Musings</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/my_page/articles/21/Random-Musings</guid>
        
        
        <category>science</category>
        
        <category>shower_thoughts</category>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
        <category>article</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
